I know a man who soars above the city every night.
أعرف رجلا يحلق في سماء المدينة كل ليلة.
In his dreams, he twirls and swirls
في أحلامه، يصول ويجول
with his toes kissing the Earth.
وأصابع أقدامه تقبل الأرض.
Everything has motion, he claims,
كل شيء يتحرك، كما يقول،
even a body as paralyzed as his own.
بما في ذلك جسم مشلول كجسمه.
This man is my father.
هذا الرجل هو أبي.
Three years ago, when I found out
قبل ثلاث سنوات، عندما علمت
that my father had suffered a severe stroke
أن أبي كان يعاني من سكتة دماغية أليمة
in his brain stem,
في جذع دماغه،
I walked into his room in the ICU
توجهت إلى غرفته في وحدة العناية المركزة
at the Montreal Neurological Institute
في المعهد العصبي لمونتريال
and found him lying deathly still,
فوجدته ممددا وكأنه ميت حي،
tethered to a breathing machine.
مربوط بجهاز تنفس.
Paralysis had closed over his body slowly,
تمكن الشلل من جسده ببطء،
beginning in his toes, then legs,
بداية من أصابع قدميه، ثم ساقيه،
torso, fingers and arms.
جذعه، أصابعه وذراعيه.
It made its way up his neck,
ثم تابع طريقه حتى وصل إلى رقبته،
cutting off his ability to breathe,
قاطعا بذلك قدرته على التنفس،
and stopped just beneath the eyes.
وتوقف فقط بين عينيه.
He never lost consciousness.
لم يفقد وعيه قط.
Rather, he watched from within
بل عاين من داخله
as his body shut down,
حين كان جسمه يتوقف عن العمل،
limb by limb,
طرفا بطرف،
muscle by muscle.
عضلة تلو الأخرى.
In that ICU room, I walked up to my father's body,
في غرفة العناية المركزة تلك، توجهت نحو جسد والدي،
and with a quivering voice and through tears,
وبصوت مرتعش تخنقه العبرات،
I began reciting the alphabet.
بدأت أقرأ عليه الحروف الهجائية.
A, B, C, D, E, F, G,
أ، ب، ت، ث، ج، ح، خ
H, I, J, K.
د ذ ر ز س
At K, he blinked his eyes.
عند حرف ك، رمشت عيناه.
I began again.
فبدأت مرة أخرى.
A, B, C, D, E, F, G,
أ، ب، ت، ث، ج، ح، خ
H, I.
ه، ي
He blinked again at the letter I,
رمشت عيناه عند حرف الياء،
then at T, then at R, and A:
بعدها على التاء، وبعدها الراء، ثم الألف:
Kitra.
كيترا.
He said "Kitra, my beauty, don't cry.
قال: "كيترا، يا حلوتي، لا تبكي.
This is a blessing."
فهذه كرامة."
There was no audible voice, but my father
لم يكن صوته مسموعا، لكن أبي
called out my name powerfully.
نادى اسمي بقوة.
Just 72 hours after his stroke,
بعد 72 ساعة فقط من السكتة الدماغية،
he had already embraced
كان قد تقبل
the totality of his condition.
حالته بمجملها.
Despite his extreme physical state,
رغم حالته الجسدية القاسية،
he was completely present with me,
كان حاضرا معي بشكل كامل،
guiding, nurturing,
يرشدني، يرعاني
and being my father as much
كان أبي بقدر
if not more than ever before.
إن لم أقل أكثر مما كان عليه من قبل.
Locked-in syndrome
متلازمة الحبس
is many people's worst nightmare.
هي أسوأ كابوس بالنسبة لمعظم الناس.
In French, it's sometimes called
بالفرنسية يطلق عليها أحيانا اسم:
"maladie de l'emmuré vivant."
"مرض المحبوس حيا خلف الجدران"
Literally, "walled-in-alive disease."
بتعبير حرفي: “مرض المحبوس حيا خلف الجدران"
For many people, perhaps most,
بالنسبة للعديد من الناس، أو ربما معظمهم،
paralysis is an unspeakable horror,
الشلل هو رعب غير قابل للنقاش،
but my father's experience
لكن تجربة أبي
losing every system of his body
الذي فقد كل جهاز في جسمه
was not an experience of feeling trapped,
لم تكن تجربة الشعور بالحصار،
but rather of turning the psyche inwards,
بل كانت تجربة تركيز على النفس من الداخل،
dimming down the external chatter,
وتعتيم على الثرثرة الخارجية،
facing the recesses of his own mind,
ومواجهة خبايا عقله،
and in that place,
وفي ذلك المكان،
falling in love with life and body anew.
الوقوع في حب الحياة والجسد من جديد.
As a rabbi and spiritual man
كحاخام ورجل روحي
dangling between mind and body, life and death,
فالتقلب بين العقل والجسد، الموت والحياة،
the paralysis opened up a new awareness for him.
والشلل فتح بين عينه آفاق وعي جديدة.
He realized he no longer needed to look
أدرك أنه لم يعد بحاجة للنظر
beyond the corporeal world
إلى ما وراء هذا العالم المادي
in order to find the divine.
لكي يجد القوة الإلهية.
"Paradise is in this body.
الجنة موجودة في هذا الجسد.
It's in this world," he said.
إنها موجودة في هذا العالم" كما يقول.
I slept by my father's side for the first four months,
نمت إلى جوار والدي خلال الأشهر الأربعة الأولى،
tending as much as I could
أحاول الوصول بقدر ما أستطيع
to his every discomfort,
إلى ضيقه،
understanding the deep human psychological fear
وأن أفهم عمق الخوف النفسي للإنسان
of not being able to call out for help.
حين لا يستطيع أن ينادي أحدا لمساعدته.
My mother, sisters, brother and I,
أحطناه أنا وأمي وأخواتي وأخي،
we surrounded him in a cocoon of healing.
في شرنقة من الشفاء.
We became his mouthpiece,
أصبحنا ننطق بلسانه،
spending hours each day reciting the alphabet
نقضي الساعات كل يوم لنلقنه الحروف
as he whispered back sermons
حين كان يهمس بالمواعظ
and poetry with blinks of his eye.
والأشعار برمش عينيه.
His room, it became our temple of healing.
أصبحت غرفته معبدا للشفاء.
His bedside became a site for those
أصبح سريره مزارا للذين
seeking advice and spiritual counsel, and through us,
يبحثون عن النصائح والمشورة الروحية، ومن خلالنا،
my father was able to speak
كان أبي يستطيع أن يتكلم،
and uplift,
وأن يرقى كلمة بكلمة،
letter by letter,
حرفا بعد حرف،
blink by blink.
رمشة تلو الأخرى.
Everything in our world became slow and tender
كل شيء في عالمنا أصبح بطيئا وحانيا
as the din, drama and death of the hospital ward
حين كانت تتلاشى الجلبة، والحزن والموت
faded into the background.
في جناح المستشفى في الخلفية.
I want to read to you one of the first things
أريد أن أقرأ لكم أحد الأشياء الأولى
that we transcribed in the week following the stroke.
التي نسخناها في خلال الأسبوع الذي تلى السكتة الدماغية.
He composed a letter,
لقد ركب رسالة،
addressing his synagogue congregation,
موجهة إلى طائفته في الكنيس،
and ended it with the following lines:
والتي ختمها بالأسطر الآتية:
"When my nape exploded,
عندما انفجرت مؤخرة عنقي،
I entered another dimension:
دخلت في بعد آخر:
inchoate, sub-planetary, protozoan.
غير متجانس وساطع وراسخ.
Universes are opened and closed continually.
تُفتَحُ الأكوان وتُغلق باستمرار.
There are many when low,
هناك العديد منها عندما تضعف
who stop growing.
تتوقف عن النمو.
Last week, I was brought so low,
في الأسبوع الماضي، ضعفت،
but I felt the hand of my father around me,
لكنني شعرت بيد والدي حولي،
and my father brought me back."
فأعادني والدي إلى الحياة."
When we weren't his voice,
حين لم نكن صوته،
we were his legs and arms.
كنا قدميه وذراعيه.
I moved them like I know I would have wanted
حركتهم كما كنت أحب أن تتحرك
my own arms and legs to be moved
ذراعي وقدمي
were they still for all the hours of the day.
من مكانها حيث ظلت لساعات طوال اليوم.
I remember I'd hold his fingers near my face,
أتذكر أنني أضع أصابعه قرب وجهي،
bending each joint to keep it soft and limber.
وأنا أجمع كلا منجها لأبقيها لينة ورشيقة.
I'd ask him again and again
كنت أطلب منه مرارا
to visualize the motion,
أن يتخيل الحركة،
to watch from within as the finger curled
أن يرى من داخله كيف يتحرك أصبعه
and extended, and to move along with it
ويتمدد وكيف يتحرك معه
in his mind.
بعقله.
Then, one day, from the corner of my eye,
بعدها، ذات يوم، رأيته بطرف عيني،
I saw his body slither like a snake,
رأيت جسده ينزلق كالأفعى،
an involuntary spasm passing through the course
كان هناك تشنج لا إرادي يمر خلال
of his limbs.
أطرافه.
At first, I thought it was my own hallucination,
في البداية ظننت أنها إحدى هلوساتي،
having spent so much time tending to this one body,
بما أنني قد قضيت وقتا طويلا في مراقبة ذلك الجسد،
so desperate to see anything react on its own.
على أمل أن أرى أي شيء يتحرك بمفرده.
But he told me he felt tingles,
لكنه أخبرني أنه أحس بوخز خفيف،
sparks of electricity flickering on and off
بشرارات كهربائية تشتعل ثم تنطفئ
just beneath the surface of the skin.
تحت سطح بشرته.
The following week, he began ever so slightly
في الأسبوع التالي بدأ بشكل طفيف
to show muscle resistance.
يظهر بعض المقاومة العضلية.
Connections were being made.
تم ربط الاتصالات جميعها.
Body was slowly and gently reawakening,
بدأ جسمه شيئا فشيئا بالاستيقاظ،
limb by limb, muscle by muscle,
طرفا بعد طرف، عضلة بعد الأخرى،
twitch by twitch.
انتفاضة بعد أخرى.
As a documentary photographer,
كمصورة وثائقية،
I felt the need to photograph
كنت أحس أنني بحاجة لكي أصور
each of his first movements
كل حركاته الأولى
like a mother with her newborn.
كما الأم مع وليدها.
I photographed him taking his first unaided breath,
صورته وهو يأخذ نفسه الأول دون مساعدة،
the celebratory moment after he showed
اللحظة الاحتفالية بعد أن أظهر
muscle resistance for the very first time,
مقاومة عضلية للمرة الأولى،
the new adapted technologies that allowed him
تلك التكنولوجيا المناسبة التي سمحت له
to gain more and more independence.
بأن يحصل على المزيد من الحرية.
I photographed the care and the love
صورت الرعاية والحب
that surrounded him.
التي كانت تحيط به.
But my photographs only told the outside story
لكن صوري تحكي فقط عن الجزء الخارجي لقصة
of a man lying in a hospital bed
رجل متمدد على سرير في مستشفى
attached to a breathing machine.
موصول بجهاز تنفس.
I wasn't able to portray his story from within,
لم أتمكن من تصوير قصته من الداخل،
and so I began to search for a new visual language,
لذا فقد بدأت في البحث عن لغة بصرية جديدة،
one which strived to express the ephemeral quality
لغة تناضل من أجل أن تعبر عن الحالة العابرة
of his spiritual experience.
لتجربته الروحية هذه.
Finally, I want to share with you
وأخيرا، أريد أن أريكم
a video from a series that I've been working on
شريطا ضمن سلاسل كنت أشتغل عليها
that tries to express the slow, in-between existence
والتي تحاول أن تفسر البطء، وحالة ما بين الحياة
that my father has experienced.
التي كان يعيشها والدي.
As he began to regain his ability to breathe,
حين بدأ في استعادة قدرته على التنفس،
I started recording his thoughts,
بدأت أسجل أفكاره،
and so the voice that you hear in this video
لذا فالصوت الذي ستسمعونه في هذا الشريط
is his voice.
هو صوته.
(Video) Ronnie Cahana: You have to believe
(شريط): روني كاهانا: عليك أن تؤمن
you're paralyzed
أنك مشلول
to play the part
لكي تلعب دورك
of a quadriplegic.
كشخص مشلول.
I don't.
لكنني لست كذلك.
In my mind,
في عقلي،
and in my dreams
وفي أحلامي
every night
كل ليلة
I Chagall-man float
أحوم مثل رجل
over the city
في سماء المدينة
twirl and swirl
أصول وأجول
with my toes kissing the floor.
وأصابع قدمي تقبل الأرض.
I know nothing about the statement
لا أدري شيئا عن تعبير
of man without motion.
رجل بدون حركة
Everything has motion.
كل شيء يتحرك.
The heart pumps.
القلب ينبض.
The body heaves.
الجسم يبذل جهدا.
The mouth moves.
الفم يتحرك.
We never stagnate.
لا نتوقف عن الحركة أبدا.
Life triumphs up and down.
ترفعنا الحياة عاليا وترمي بنا أرضا.
Kitra Cahana: For most of us,
كيترا كاهانا: بالنسبة لمعظمنا
our muscles begin to twitch and move
فعضلاتنا تبدأ بالانتفاض والتحرك
long before we are conscious,
قبل أن ننتبه لها،
but my father tells me his privilege
لكن أني أخبرني أن ميزته
is living on the far periphery
أنه عاش في المحيط الخارجي البعيد
of the human experience.
للتجربة الإنسانية.
Like an astronaut who sees a perspective
مثل رائد فضاء يرى أفقا
that very few of us will ever get to share,
أمكن للقليلين منا تقاسمه،
he wonders and watches as he takes
كان يتساءل ويرى حين كان يلتقط
his first breaths
أنفاسه الأولى
and dreams about crawling back home.
وكان يحلم بالعودة إلى المنزل.
So begins life at 57, he says.
وهكذا بدأت الحياة في سن 57 كما يقول.
A toddler has no attitude in its being,
لا يملك طفل صغير موقفا في حد ذاته،
but a man insists on his world every day.
لكن الرجل من يصر على عالمه كل يوم.
Few of us will ever have to face physical limitations
قليلون من سيواجهون قط إعاقات جسدية
to the degree that my father has,
بالدرجة التي عانى منها والدي،
but we will all have moments of paralysis
ولكننا سنعاني من لحظات شلل
in our lives.
في حياتنا.
I know I frequently confront walls
أعلم أنني أصطدم بجدران
that feel completely unscalable,
يصعب تسلقها تماما،
but my father insists
لكن أبي أصر
that there are no dead ends.
أنه ليست هناك طريق مسدودة.
Instead, he invites me into his space of co-healing
بالمقابل، فقد دعاني إلى فضائه حيث الشفاء المشترك
to give the very best of myself, and for him
لأعطيه أفضل ما لدي، وبالنسبة له
to give the very best of himself to me.
ليعطيني أفضل ما لديه.
Paralysis was an opening for him.
كان الشلل بوابة بالنسبة له.
It was an opportunity to emerge,
كانت فرصة لينبثق،
to rekindle life force,
ليحيي قوة الحياة مرة أخرى،
to sit still long enough with himself
ليظل مزيدا من الوقت مع نفسه
so as to fall in love with the full continuum
وبذلك يقع في حب التواصل الكامل
of creation.
مع الكون.
Today, my father is no longer locked in.
اليوم لم يعد أبي محبوسا.
He moves his neck with ease,
فهو يحرك رقبته بسهولة،
has had his feeding peg removed,
وقد أُزيلت روابط التغذية الخاصة به،
breathes with his own lungs,
وهو يتنفس برئتيه،
speaks slowly with his own quiet voice,
ويتحدث ببطء بصوته الهادئ،
and works every day
ويعمل كل يوم
to gain more movement in his paralyzed body.
لكي يحصل على مزيد من الحركة من جسمه المشلول.
But the work will never be finished.
لكن العمل لن ينتهي أبدا.
As he says, "I'm living in a broken world,
كما يقول؛"أن أعيش في عالم فاسد،
and there is holy work to do."
وهناك عمل مقدس يجب القيام به."
Thank you.
شكرا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)